Okay, so in this video
then we are going to
introduce the concept of risk management.
Now let's define risk.
A risk is an uncertainty.
It's an uncertainty that may or may not
happen.
That's what a risk is.
It may happen or it may not happen.
If we know it's going to happen,
it's not a risk anymore.
Now it's an issue.
So that is a basic difference between a
risk and an issue.
A risk is it's always it may happen,
right?
It may happen or it may not happen.
An issue is either it's happened or it
will happen.
It's imminent.
So that is a basic difference in a risk
and an issue.
So a risk is always a future uncertain
event, right?
That may or may not happen.
Now, generally, we think of a risk as
being negative.
But a risk can also be positive.
a positive risk is known as an
opportunity.
So you have the opportunity to save money
on a project.
There's an opportunity material prices
might come down.
It may happen, it may not happen.
But if it happens and we save money on our
project, that's a good thing.
We may get favourable exchange rates,
right, and our currency.
Again, it may happen, it may not happen.
But if it happens, it's a good thing.
So, a risk is always, always an
uncertainty.
So a positive risk is known as an
opportunity.
Rather than an opportunity, you know, it's
something positive,
something good could happen.
A negative risk is known of the threat.
So on most risks,
like I said, we generally
tend to think of risks as being negative.
So a risk then is always a future
uncertain event.
and if it materializes, it may have a
positive or negative impact on the project.
Now, an issue is always negative.
An issue is always considered
being negative, and you
don't have a positive issue,
an issue is always negative.
Remember, an issue is a negative risk that
is either materialized
or will materialize.
It's either happened or it will happen.
It's imminent.
And so, one of the key roles then as a
project manager, right?
is you want to try and minimize or
eliminate a negative risk.
You want to eliminate or minimize a threat
to a project.
Eliminate a negative risk.
If you can't always eliminate it, but we
certainly want to try
and minimize the effect.
But if there's a positive risk,
we want to try and maximize the potential
of getting a positive risk, of getting an
opportunity.
If material prices are going to come down,
we want to take advantage of that.
Now, you are not
going to identify all of the
risks, right, the
beginning of the project.
You're going to be identifying risks
throughout your project, right?
So risks are going to emerge throughout
the project lifecycle.
These are known as emergent risks,
right?
They're going to be emerging.
So you need to make your project resilient
to these risks.
We need to have project resilience.
We need to identify potential issues
before they occur.
We want to identify risks before they
materialize into an issue.
And so we have a plan to
deal with them, something
that's mentioned also
in quality management.
We want to put preventive actions in
place.
We want to try and eliminate any kind of
issues.
I want to try and make sure issues don't
occur in the first place.
So if there are any potential issues,
we have a plan to deal with it.
And a potential issue, if it's a potential
issue, it's a risk.
Again, it may or may not happen.
So as a general rule, if you have a good
risk management process in place,
then usually you have a good quality
management process in place.
Just as a general, you know, just as a
very high level general rule.
because you are identifying potential
issues that could occur.
So, again, that's all part of building
quality into your project, right,
into your product, into your organization.
So we want to regularly
seek out early warning signs,
right, of something that
could trigger a risk, right?
We want to be proactive.
We want to identify potential causes of
failure throughout our project.
we're going to frequently communicate,
review any of these emergent risks,
understand them, see
what the potential impact
is or what the potential impact could be.
We want to make sure we have enough
contingency reserves, make sure we have
enough money in our contingency reserves
to pay for the risks, make sure we have a
good procedure, proper procedure,
contingency reserve procedure.
If we need to put more
money in contingency
reserves, then what is
the procedures for that?
So again, risk management
is something that you
do actually throughout
the entire project process.
It's not something you just do here and
there, right?
Risk management is not, or we'll figure it
out if it happens, or
we'll just deal with it.
That is not risk management.
In fact, that's not really management at
all, right?
Figure it out if you go along is not
managing a project.
Right, anybody can do that.
But no, we want to have a good,
proper risk management process in place,
right, throughout our project.
So risk planning should start right at the
beginning, right at the
inception of the project.
Right, you're going to start
thinking about what risks are
out there and how we're going
to manage and control risk.
In fact, even as part of the business
case, you start thinking about risks,
right, about all of the risks on your
project.
But risk management continues all the way
throughout the project.
You never, never stop identifying risks on
your project.
okay